hello and welcome this is active live
stream number 52.0 and it is February
28th 2023.
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
you can find us at the links here on
this slide this is a recorded at an
archived live stream so please provide
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will be following video
etiquette for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org if you want to learn
more
and participate in learning groups and
projects at The Institute including
these live streams
well
we're here today to learn and discuss
the paper
geometric methods for sampling
optimization inference and adaptive
agents by Alessandro Barb Lancelot
DeCosta gujarme Franca Carl friston Mark
giralami Michael Jordan and gregorios
pavliotis
this video like all.zero videos are
is a introduction for some of the ideas
it is not a review or a final word and
as We've joked before it's more than
anything a call for help so if you're
curious about these topics if you're
knowledgeable about these topics we
would really look forward to you getting
involved in the upcoming 52.1 and 52.2
discussions as well as in an ongoing
basis to help us understand some of the
technical details
this is going to get technical at times
and certainly beyond the technicalities
I understand though I am looking forward
to presenting them
and it'll be great to have those who
have backgrounds of all different types
to come together and talk about this
awesome work
also a big thanks to Ali and Camden for
the assistance Technical and moral
during the preparations here
in 52.0 we're going to bring up some
aims and claims read the abstract look
at the road map and talk about the
keywords and then we will walk through
the paper with an emphasis on the
figures formalisms and key points in the
coming weeks we're going to be
discussing this paper with one or more
authors so as usual
get in touch if you want to participate
or if it's after the fact
you can still get involved
we can start with an introduction or a
warm-up
I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California and
I'm tempted to say just totally honestly
I'm happy to get this one over with but
that sounds a little bit different than
I might intend it to be I'm really
excited to dive into this work which is
going to be approaching active inference
from an angle that we haven't
necessarily highlighted on these streams
so I think it's going to be a
fascinating discussion it's going to run
the gamut span the gap however you
choose to see it between
technical sophistication and intuition
which is a great place to be so I've
been really excited and motivated to
prepare and I'm looking forward to the
dot zero we're doing right now and to
the upcoming discussions
so let's jump in with the big questions
that might motivate one to read this
paper this kind of paper even if they
were not familiar with the authors or
topics and these are just a few ways to
write it up of course not the only ways
so first question
how can we effectively and efficiently
navigate information geometric or
information theoretic Landscapes and how
can we tackle that question from an
analytical which is to say equation
based as well as a computational which
is to say real implementation based
perspective
often it's really
fun intuitive natural to talk about
information Theory even for those who
haven't taken the technical
prerequisites and this work may help us
navigate to a space where we're able to
think with good intuitions about
information geometry information Theory
and also make sure that those intuitions
are going to be caught by our technical
tools
second how can we optimize inference in
complex models including cases where we
are doing inference on action as a
parameter also known as active inference
optimization and functional analysis as
we'll come to see soon has long been
interested in these complex or
challenging models that are right at the
margin right at the border of what is
tractable or not given the computational
hardware that modelers have access to
for example big data sets High
dimensional State spaces complex
Dynamics and so on
how about cases where we're also
interested in doing parametric inference
and optimization on action or action
plans as a parameter also known as
active inference
and third what technical underpinnings
support the rigor and applicability of
active inference
and what special cases are revealed when
we consider possibilities and
constraints
these are those two branches of
analytical and computational coming back
again we want to make sure that when
we're thinking within the active
inference Paradigm the active inference
ontology is the language that we're
speaking and that there's a technical
rigor to what's being discussed
additionally we want to make sure that
it's not just an analytical rigor but
it's also going to be computationally
plausible
tractable or maybe even preferable that
would be awesome
those are the questions that at least
appeared
we are discussing this paper geometric
methods for sampling optimization
inference and adaptive agents
by Barb and Acosta at all shared first
authorship and it was published on
archive
I'll just note a few key claims from
this paper
they wrote our goal in this chapter is
to discuss the emergence of natural
geometries within a few important areas
of statistics and Applied Mathematics
namely optimization sampling inference
and adoptive agents that's the title
we provide a conceptual introduction to
the underlying ideas rather than a
technical discussion highlighting
connections with various fields of
mathematics and physics well I can tell
you that they do make connections with
various fields of mathematics and
physics though whether it is a
conceptual introduction or a technical
discussion is all going to be about your
perspective
third to illustrate a generic use case
for the previous methodologies that are
going to be discussed we consider active
inference a unifying formulation of
behavior subsuming perception planning
and learning as a process of inference
so inference on adaptive agents is not
necessarily new it goes by reinforcement
learning machine learning and so on
however to use those methodologies in
the context of active inference a
unifying formulation of behavior is
something that the authors are bringing
forth here
and last we describe decision making
under active inference using information
geometry revealing several special cases
that are established Notions in
statistics cognitive science and
engineering so active inference is not
just unifying it's going to be shown to
be generalized as well which is to say
that special cases of the generalization
emerge
different formalisms that were known
disparately across fields
on to the abstract
they write
in this chapter we identify fundamental
geometric structures that underlie the
problems of sampling optimization
inference and adaptive decision making
based on this identification we derive
algorithms that exploit these geometric
structures to solve these problems
efficiently
we show that a wide range of geometric
theories emerge naturally in these
fields ranging from measure preserving
processes information divergences
poisson geometry and geometric
integration
specifically we explain how
one leveraging the simplectic geometry
of hamiltonian systems enable us to
construct accelerated sampling and
optimization methods
two the theory of hilbertian subspaces
and Stein operators provides a general
methodology to obtain robust estimators
and three preserving the information
geometry of decision making yields
adaptive agents that perform active
inference
throughout we emphasize the rich
connections between these fields EG
inference draws on sampling and
optimization and adaptive decision
making assesses decisions by inferring
their counterfactual consequences
our Exposition provides a conceptual
overview of underlying ideas rather than
a technical discussion which can be
found in the references herein and
indeed there are several hundred
references in this paper
let's go to the roadmap so first we can
start on the right side
here's an active agent vroom vroom
doing accelerated optimization in the
carpool lane looking ahead to the almost
dessert-like visual representation of
active inference
that's where we're gonna go
and on the right side it's just some
cars one of them is accelerated the
other one isn't
the paper begins with an introduction
and then in section two gets into the
topic of accelerated optimization
covering the areas of principle of
geometric integration conservative flows
and symplectic integrators rate matching
integrators for smooth optimization
manifold and constrained optimization
gradient flow is a high friction limit
and optimization on the space of
probability measures
in section three they turn from
accelerated optimization in general to
hamiltonian-based accelerated sampling
the subsections of three are optimizing
diffusion processes for sampling and
hamiltonian Monte Carlo
from The hamiltonian-based Accelerated
sampling they turn towards doing
statistical inference with kernel based
discrepancies in section 4. the
subsections are topological methods for
mmds smooth measures and ksds the
canonical Stein operator and poincare
duality
Colonel Stein discrepancies and score
matching
information geometry of mmds and natural
gradient descent
minimum Stein discrepancy estimators
likelihood inference with generative
models
finally in Section 5 adaptive agents
through active inference they're going
to bring it home to active inference
section 5.1 modeling adaptive decision
making Behavior agents and environments
decision making in precise agents the
information geometry of decision making
and 5.2 realizing adoptive agents the
basic active inference algorithm
sequential decision making under
uncertainty World model learning as
inference and scaling active inference
a quick note
we have all the formalisms entered into
r.0 teams Coda document there are 46
numbered equations in this paper and 83
overall
we're going to bring in some but not all
of these formalisms in the dot zero
video and were ready to bring in more
during the dot 1 and Dot two discussions
with the authors
just for those who are watching along
I'm going to scan through all of the
formalisms from our Coda and again for
those who want to help get involved with
a DOT zero preparation this is a little
bit of what zero preparation looks like
I'm going to now scroll through the
formalisms just in case anybody wants to
screenshot or see them
great
on to the keywords
keywords of the paper are information
geometry hamiltonian Monte Carlo Stein's
method reproducing kernel variational
inference accelerated optimization
dissipative systems decision Theory and
active inference
in no particular pedagogical order
let's start with decision Theory
from the Stanford encyclopedia a
philosophy the article begins decision
theory is concerned with the reasoning
underlying an agent's choices whether
this is a mundane choice between taking
the bus or getting a taxi or a more
far-reaching choice about whether to
pursue a demanding political career
decision theory is about agents making
decisions cognitive things making
decisions
and we can take a peek ahead to figure
three which is shown here as well as
invoke some of the keywords that we're
about to walk into now so if this is
your first time hearing some of this
vocabulary or you're super familiar
either way it's great
in this paper and in this discussion
we're going to see how different
decision theoretic settings
such as no ambiguity no ambiguity or no
preference no extrinsic value and no
intrinsic value
are going to be operationalized within
an information theoretic formalism in
information geometric formalism
and specifically one that we're able to
do accelerated inference on using
variational methods
we're going to be involving action as a
parameter so we can call that octave
inference and that's how we're
approaching decision Theory and getting
from here to there with all those fun
stops in between let's go to information
Theory
the paper in the introduction writes of
particular relevance to this chapter is
information geometry
EG the differential geometric treatment
of smooth statistical manifolds
whose origin stems from a seminal
article by Rao 23 who introduced the
Fischer metric tensor unparameterized
statistical models
and thus a natural ramanian geometry
that was later observed to correspond to
an infinitesimal distance with respect
to the kobach libler or KL Divergence
so going into citation 23 and 24.
citation 23 is Rao from 1992 and Rao
wrote the objective of the paper is to
derive certain inequality relations
connecting the elements of the
information Matrix as defined by Fisher
1921 and the variances and covariances
of the estimating functions a class of
distribution functions which admit an
estimation of parameters with the
minimum possible variance has been
discussed
the concept of distance between
populations of a given type has been
developed starting from a quadratic
differential metric defining the element
of length so I'm only going to give the
disclaimer one time everything in red
text is beyond speculative it's just
priming the pump for discussions with
those who know more and with those who
know less and it's just a first pass
that we're going to continue to develop
on but broadly if we can compute
inequality relationships which this
paper developed in 1992
we can bound estimators test for
relative improvements and basically do
stuff with those distributions
and if we can compute certain kinds of
statistical distances such that a
distance requires a length metric
we can find Optimal estimated estimators
of parameters specifically their
variances and covariance structure
in principle and in practice
by finding that maximum informational
alignments to other estimators or
empirical data so we'll often say like
if you had the optimum parameterization
you'd be predicting as well as you could
and so we want to be able to
operationalize that using distances and
metrics
and citation 24.
this is an invariant form for the prior
probability and estimation Problems by
Harold Jeffries and Jeffries wrote it
has shown that a certain differential
form depending on the values of the
parameters in a law of chance
is invariant for all transformations of
the parameters when the law is
differentiable with regard to all
parameters for laws containing a
location in the scale parameter a form
with a somewhat restricted type of
invariance is found even when the law is
not everywhere differentiable with
regard to the parameters
this form has the properties required to
give a general rule for stating the
prior probability in a large class of
estimation problems so if all the
parameters in our model whether there's
one two or more are differentiable which
is to say they're smooth
etc etc there are technical details then
there are certain transformational
invariances so just like every gaussian
distribution by shifting it and
stretching and shrinking it you can map
those onto each other it's like that
it turns out that some of those
constraints can even be somewhat relaxed
for example this approach may still be
effective even where parameters are not
differentiable everywhere
and this is big for helping us do
Bayesian estimation which can be seen as
a special case of informational
Transformations or of manipulations of
statistical distributions
in the information theoretic or
information geometric sense
functional analysis so let's begin as
tradition in our year 2023 with a brief
quote from chat GPT
how is functional analysis helpful for
us who are learning and applying active
inference I'll just read the last
section overall functional analysis
provides a powerful mathematical toolset
for understanding and analyzing the
principles of active inference
and one can read more
functional analysis is the study of
functions and here we see one way of
showing what a function does in terms of
being this box f of x that takes in an
input in argument X and outputs a result
Y and also that can be understood as a
mapping
between or amongst spaces and there's a
lot more to go into just wanted to bring
up that in math sometimes people have
analyzed functions and their properties
and we're interested in the properties
of a special class of functions which
are probability distributions
well-behaved probability distributions
what do we do with those probability
distributions well one thing we might
want to do is sample so the paper writes
sampling methods are critical to the
efficient implementations of many
methodologies
most modern Samplers are based on Markov
chain Monte Carlo methods which include
slice Samplers piecewise deterministic
Markov chains and so on
the original hamiltonian Monte Carlo or
HMC which we're going to get to
algorithm was introduced in physics to
sample distributions on gauge groups for
lattice quantum chromodynamics
it combined two approaches that emerged
in previous decades namely the
Metropolis Hastings algorithm and the
hamiltonian formulation of molecular
Dynamics
so the way that they stated in the
beginning of Section 3 of the paper is
the purpose of sampling methods is to
efficiently draw samples from a given
Target distribution rho or more commonly
to calculate expectations with respect
to row by equation 33 and other
they write modern hamiltonian Monte
Carlo which again we're going to get to
in a second relies heavily on some
plectic integrators another keyword
to simulate a deterministic dynamic
responsible for generating distant moves
between samples and thus reduce their
correlation while at the same time
preserving important geometric
properties
now
we want to make our samples as
informative as possible if we're just
drawing samples and it's the same sample
again and again one can imagine that it
is uninformative
conversely one can imagine a situation
where samples are informative
and that
is brought into practice by making sure
that the samples are minimally
correlated with each other as noted
above
and this also has analogy in
cryptography so if we're sampling
something where the successive samples
are 99 correlated you can imagine that
you're over sampling so you're taking 10
000 frames per second of a YouTube video
with 30 frames per second I think I'm
streaming at 25 frames per second right
now
conversely if one were to sample every
10 minutes then their correlation
structure would also not capture the
videos 25 frames per second
so in order to generate good and large
moves in the space
we would need perfect knowledge of what
the space is or how it's generated which
is sometimes knowable in cryptography
however empirically we need to use
heuristics and statistical
approximations so this is the applied
statistics angle on the analytical
relationships that we're going to be
talking about and it's going to come up
again and again this tension between
analytical formulations what's true in
principle and the statistical or
numerical or computational applications
two hamiltonian Monte Carlo
from Wikipedia
the hamiltonian Monte Carlo algorithm
originally known as hybrid Monte Carlo
still HMC is a Markov chain Monte Carlo
method for obtaining a sequence of
random samples which converge to being
distributed according to a Target
probability distribution for which
direct sampling is difficult
so just a few first pass Reflections
we're sampling which is to say Monte
Carlo and Monte Carlo is hearkening back
to a different time when gambling was
done in Monte Carlo and the state space
of all the hands of poker were too vast
to compute analytically or equations
were not known and so what one used to
do and still does is draw samples and
say well I don't know if this is the
final estimate on How likely a royal
flush is but from the 2 billion hands
that I sampled there were two Royal
flushes and so it's one in a billion
based upon my sample
so we're sampling because this is a
complex distribution for which an
analytical solution is not possible not
known not relevant or not tractable
computationally so there's various
situations where we want to sample and
we don't necessarily have an analytical
solution
when we're sampling from a converged
stationarity hashtag livestream 26 of a
statistical landscape
from a numerical perspective we
understand that landscape well enough to
do inference so imagine that we're
sampling height estimates
from GPS locations in the X and the Y
coordinates and we're getting a z value
in our sample
at some point we can say
were unsurprised by new samples
at that point we understand the
landscape well enough to do statistical
inference and just like the frames per
second in the previous example one can
imagine if the landscape is changing on
the spatial scale of one mile and you're
sampling every millimeter you might be
over sampling if you were sampling every
League maybe you'd be too coarse grained
with your samples
and so one reason that comes up in
science all the time for using sampling
is that the search space might be just
too large
for example the combinatorics of a
phylogenetic tree with a thousand
species might be vast and so it might be
better to say something like well 99 of
the million samples we drew were
consistent with x
because an analytical solution or a
Brute Force search neither might be
possible
and the Wikipedia route this sequence of
samples can be used to estimate
integrals with respect to the Target
distribution
so sometimes we're sampling not from the
target distribution itself but rather
from a distribution that is related or
transformed from the target distribution
this is because sampling directly from a
target distribution might be difficult
or less than perfectly informative
so we might for example
hint hint sample from the derivative of
the target which might help us identify
points where for example the derivative
is flat in all directions
in the case that we're sampling from a
derived landscape of the target
distribution this is called a simplectic
integrator
so let's look at what a simplectic
integrator is
so
first backing up to what is differential
geometry differential geometry is a
mathematical discipline that studies the
geometry of smooth shapes and smooth
spaces otherwise known as smooth
manifolds
simplexic geometry is a branch of
differential geometry and differential
topology that studies simplexic
manifolds that is differentiable
manifolds equipped with a closed
non-degenerate to form
symplectic geometry has its origins in
the hamiltonian formulation of classical
mechanics where the phase space of
certain classical systems takes on the
structure of a simplectic manifold so
the keyword density is high these topics
are all very closely linked
from the paper it has been known for a
long time that the class of symplectic
integrators is the preferred choice for
simulating physical systems only the
finest for our simulations of physical
systems
these discretization techniques are
designed to preserve the underlying
symplectic geometry of hamiltonian
systems and they also form the bases of
hamiltonian Monte Carlo or hybrid Monte
Carlo methods
we're going to come back to this tension
again and again which is what good
is a in principle smooth and
differentiable analytical formulation if
our discretization scheme the way that
we actually implement the steps
on a computer
are inferior we might ruin all those
nice properties that we work to get
about the analytical form we might just
throw those out when we discretize it
coarsely or inappropriately
so what is a simplectic integrator it's
a numerical integration scheme for
hamiltonian systems
symplectic integrators form the subclass
of geometric integrators which by
definition are canonical transformations
their Transformations we know a lot
about
simplexic integrator schemes
are referring to
again just broadly
both the analytical formulations and the
software packages and approaches that we
can use to implement those formalisms
and these integration schemes are useful
across difficult estimation problems
which is why they're used to study
non-linear Dynamics molecular Dynamics
like protein simulation discrete element
methods accelerator physics plasma
physics quantum physics Celestial
mechanics
the time evolution of Hamilton's
equation is a simplexomorphism
meaning that it conserves the symplectic
to form
a numerical scheme is a simplectic
integrator if it also conserves this to
form
let's hear more if this is not correct
or not complete but the one form is like
the differentiation and integration of a
line the two form is like the
differentiation and integration of a
surface and the three form is like
integration or differentiation of a
volume
and John Denker has a great blog post on
the basic properties of a simplectic
integrator
some really interesting quotes that are
good to just keep in mind when we're
hearing about all these Avenues we're
going to be exploring in the paper
a simplectic integrator conserves the
area in Phase Space delimited by an
ensemble of systems
for a periodic system there is an area
that is conserved namely the area inside
the phase space orbit of the system
the main reason for mentioning the orbit
is to make the point that there are lots
of different things with dimensions of
area in Phase space some are conserved
and some not
some are interesting and some not you
have to specify which sort of area you
are talking about so
another thing that's going to arise is
we're interested in very well behaved
outcomes
from a very specific or constrained
still broad but definitely constrained
set of distributions for example
distributions that can be interpreted in
an information Theory sense as
probability distributions
what was that mention of the hamiltonian
and the shadow hamiltonian
so the author is right
four simplistic brackets which is the
kind of operation that reflects the
simplexic integrator the existence of a
shadow hamiltonian can be guaranteed
beyond the case of splitting methods EG
for variational integrators
which use variational inference
which use a discrete version of
Hamilton's principle of least action and
we've heard it before that free energy
principle is a principle of least action
for inference and action
and more generally for most simplexic
integrators in which the symplectic
bracket is preserved up to topological
considerations described by some
technicalities that we can learn about
as we shall see
such geometric integrators can be
constructed by leveraging the shadow
hamiltonian property of simplexic
methods
on higher dimensional conservative
hamiltonian systems
in short as a consequence of having
shadow hamiltonian
such geometric integrators are able to
reproduce all the relevant properties of
the Continuum system
these arguments are completely General
so
even before one knows what the shadow
hamiltonian necessarily is
the authors are letting us know that
if we can discretize the shadow
hamiltonian appropriately
through simplexic integration we can
provide discretization scheme that ends
up staying consistent and compatible and
all down the middle with the analytical
properties that we worked so hard to get
and there are some different papers that
were cited and some that were found
during research
this paper time step in Shadow
hamiltonian and molecular Dynamics
simulations by Kim
demonstrates simplexic integrators on
the simplest possible system a simple
harmonic oscillator so if one wants to
go to a technical example but one that
builds intuition that's a great place to
start
and from the Wikipedia article on energy
drift these integrators do not in fact
reproduce the actual hamiltonian
mechanics of the system instead they
reproduce a closely related Shadow
hamiltonian whose value they conserved
many orders of magnitude more closely
the accuracy of the energy conservation
to the true hamiltonian is dependent on
the time step so if we can
for example just metaphorically speaking
capture a high resolution image of the
Shadow then we'll be able to know
something do something with the actual
some technical details on Stein's method
which is a general method in probability
Theory to obtain bounds on the distance
between two probability distributions
with respect to a probability metric and
Stein's method is used in the context of
Stein operators and Stein class which
we're going to get to in the subsequent
discussions
reproducing kernel our discussion of
inference builds upon the theory of
hilbertian subspaces and in particular
reproducing kernels these inference
schemes rely on the continuity of linear
functionals such as probability and
shorts distributions
over a class of functions to geometryize
the analysis of integral probability
metrics which measure the worst case
integration error
we shall explain how maximum mean
kernelized and score matching
discrepancies arise naturally from
topological considerations so we've
added some background links here's the
slide
but it'll be a great place to start with
authors
what is a reproducing kernel
and how is it used in this paper
onwards through the keywords we go
accelerated optimization and variational
inference so here's a 2016 paper from
Michael Jordan and other authors and
some quotes from The Abstract
accelerated methods achieve faster
convergence rates than gradient methods
and indeed under certain conditions they
achieve optimal rates
however accelerated methods are not
descent methods and remain a conceptual
mystery
we propose a variational continuous time
framework for understanding accelerated
methods
we provide a systematic methodology for
converting accelerated higher order
methods from continuous time to discrete
time
our work illuminates a class of dynamics
that may be useful for Designing better
algorithms for optimization
and this is going to be again something
awesome to discuss
we've talked about on many streams
variational inference in the context of
gradient based
optimization for example the ball is
rolling to the bottom of the bowl bottom
of the hill and what you can do is you
can take the gradient div grad curl and
all that
of where the ball is and just go
downhill and if you designed the hill to
be the right shape or you're using a
chosen family of variational estimators
that are the right shape are a good
shape well-behaved shape then you follow
the gradient on down and that's how
we've talked about variational inference
accelerated optimization is going to be
accelerated from that and so it's fun to
think about and it'll be great to talk
about
dissipative systems the vast majority of
statistics and machine learning
applications involve solving
optimization problems
the author is Right accelerated gradient
based methods and several variations
thereof have become workhorses in these
fields
recently there has been great interest
in studying such methods from a
continuous time limiting perspective
such methods can be seen as first order
integrators to a classical hamiltonian
system with dissipation this raises the
question
on how to discretize the system such
that important properties are preserved
assuming the system has fast conversions
to critical point and desirable
stability properties
originally such a theory of geometric
integration was developed with
conservative systems in mind while
optimization
in optimization the associated system is
naturally a dissipative one
more recently it has been proved to the
generalization of simplexic integrators
to dissipative hamiltonian systems is
indeed able to preserve rates of
conversions and stability which are the
main properties of interest for
optimization
so
from the Wikipedia on hamiltonian
systems
an example of a Time independent
hamiltonian system is the harmonic
oscillator so it's just a frictionless
spring oscillating around
the hamiltonian of the system does not
depend on time and thus the energy of a
system is conserved and so we can say
that that is a conservative hamiltonian
if the hamiltonian decays in time it is
dissipative
recently the advances of these authors
and others have extended our ability to
make discretizations of dissipative
hamiltonians that respect
the rates of conversions and stability
which are the main properties of
interest for optimization
and we've talked about hamiltonians on
live stream number 49 with Dalton sativa
DeVille ondasia mechanics so pretty cool
what is conservative what is dissipative
we'll explore as the final keyword
here
I just wanted to start with a blank
slide on active inference and see what
happens in 52.1 so consider the slide to
be blank and for the authors and discuss
ants looking forward to hearing
how are we approaching active inference
given everything that we've just loaded
onto the table and everywhere that we're
about to go with the paper let's get
into it section one introduction
so
the authors begin with
differential geometry
place a fundamental role in Applied
Mathematics statistics and computer
science including various domains
citations 1 through 22 which can be
shown here various citations from this
well cited paper
the geometric study of statistical
models has had many successes ranging
from statistical inference where it was
used to prove the optimality of Maximum
likelihood estimator
to the construction of the category of
mathematical statistics generated by
Markov morphisms so what are Markov
morphisms from ncat Lab
the formalism of Markov categories
can be thought of as a way to express
certain aspects of probability and
statistics synthetically
in other words it consists of structure
and axioms which one can think of as
fundamental in probability and
statistics
which one can use to prove theorems
without having to use measure Theory
directly
intuitively for the purposes of
probability
a Markov category can be seen as a
category where morphisms behave like
random functions or Markov kernels hence
the name
so just some red text speculation
it was a big success and a breakthrough
to think about the category from a
formal category theoretic perspective
to think about the category of
statistical distributions from an
information geometric perspective
this means that we can understand many
analytical properties and
transformations of statistical
distributions hashtag Bayesian
and develop General methods that work
for that whole category like accelerated
optimization
and the applications are vast
originally such a theory of geometric
integration was developed with
conservative systems in mind
while in optimization the associated
system is naturally a dissipative one
nevertheless simplistic integrators were
exploited in this context
more recently it has been proved that a
generalization of simplistic integrators
to dissipative hamiltonian systems is
indeed able to preserve rates of
convergence and stability
which are the main properties of
interest for optimization so citation 9
what is it about
2021 paper on dissipative symplectic
integration with applications to
gradient-based optimization by some of
the authors
and it's interesting to pull out some
quotes from the abstract and just hear a
little bit about what they're up to
recently continuous time dynamical
systems have proved useful in providing
conceptual and quantitative insights
into gradient-based optimization widely
used in modern machine learning and
statistics
an important question that arises in
this line of work is how to discretize
the system in such a way that its
stability and rates of convergence are
preserved so this is the sampling
problem in continuous time the math is
continuous and nice
however the sampling problem which
actually comes into play when we use
modern computational methods that are
implemented on discrete time space and
constraints
what happens when we use unconventional
computing that's an interesting
discussion question but in practice
today
the discretization approach is going to
matter a lot
in this paper we propose a geometric
framework in which such discretizations
can be realized systematically enabling
the derivation of rate matching
algorithms without the need for a
discrete convergence analysis
more specifically we show that a
generalization of symplectic integrators
to non-conservative and in particular
dissipative hamiltonian systems is able
to preserve rates of convergence up to a
controlled error so this is the advance
of this paper that within a controlled
error good enough they can model
conservative and non-conservative even
dissipative hamiltonian systems
moreover such methods preserve a shadow
hamiltonian despite the absence of a
conservation law extending key results
of simplexic integrators to
non-conservative cases our arguments
rely on a combination of backwards error
analysis with fundamental results from
simplexic geometry
we stress that although the original
motivation for this work was the
application of optimization where
dissipative systems play a natural role
they are fully General and not only
provide a differential geometric
analysis for dissipative hamiltonian
systems but also substantially extend
the theory of structure preserving
integration
so they made this generalization in the
case of optimization however it's
exciting that it extends even deeper
into the math and the symmetry
those are a few highlights from section
one
on to section 2 accelerated optimization
vroom vroom here we go
so
there are going to be a lot of slides
from sections two through five and to
keep the video a reasonable length I'm
going to just highlight a few pieces not
even necessarily what I intended to
highlight but I'm just going to go for
it so we can get through it
section two we shall be concerned with a
problem of optimization of a function
finding a point that maximizes V of Q or
minimizes negative V of Q over a smooth
manifold m r in the real numbers
many algorithms and optimization are
given as a sequence of finite
differences
even when these algorithms are seen
as discretizations of a Continuum system
whose behavior is presumably understood
it is well known that most
discretizations break important
properties of a system and they continue
to write the analysis of such finite
difference iterations is usually
challenging relying on painstaking
algebra to obtain theoretical guarantees
such as conversions to a critical point
stability and rates of conversions to a
critical point
even when these algorithms are seen as
discretizations of a continuous system
whose behavior is presumably understood
it is well known that most
discretizations break important
properties of the system
it can't be highlighted enough
when we Implement optimization
algorithms on Modern computers we have
to make discretizations in space and
time and in practice so even if the
analytical properties of the
distribution are totally fire
when we try to solve and fit models to
empirical data
unless we also match that elegance and
power with the discretization approach
we end up failing to realize analytical
promises
2.1 the principle of geometric
integration
fortunately the authors write here comes
into play one of the most fundamental
ideas of geometric Integrations
many numerical integrators are very
close exponentially in the step size to
a smooth Dynamics generated by a shadow
Vector field
a little Whisper of a shadow hamiltonian
and the shadow Vector field is a
perturbation of the original Vector
field
this allows us to analyze the discrete
trajectory implemented by the algorithm
using powerful tools from dynamical
systems and differential geometry which
are a priori reserved to smooth Systems
so we're going to be able to discretize
our cake and have it be smooth too
crucially while numerical integrators
typically diverge significantly from the
Dynamics they aim to simulate geometric
integrators respect the main properties
of a system
in the context of optimization this
means respecting stability and rates of
convergence seems like a good idea to
respect the main properties of the
system
this was first demonstrated in nine and
further extended in 10. our discussion
will be based on Dean's work so
citation 9 Franca Jordan and Vidal
mentioned previously and Citation 10
Franca barp giralami and Jordan
optimization on manifolds a simplectic
approach authors previous work so big
development
we can use geometric rather than
coarse numerical integrators so our
sampling based optimization schemes
including their discretization respect
the main properties of the system sounds
great
section 2.2 conservative flows and
symplectic integrators as a stepping
stone we first discussed the
construction of suitable conservative
flows
these are very well studied and they're
very intuitive
more intuitive
to construct Vector Fields along the
derivative of x which is the function of
flows along which some function is
constant
we shall need brackets geometrically
these are morphisms X star to X also
known as contravariant tensors of Rank 2
in physics so calling back the two
form
and the brackets
importantly Vector fields that preserve
F correspond to bracket Vector fields in
which B is anti-symmetric
constructing conservative flows is thus
straightforward
unfortunately it is a rather more
challenging task to construct efficient
discretizations that retain this
property
most well-known procedures namely
discrete gradient and projection methods
only give rise to integrators that
require solving implicit equations at
every step and they may other they may
break other important properties of the
system
citation 96.
this is the issue again no matter how
nicely behaved in principle are
analytical underlying smooth
differentiable function is if we
discretize it and we chop it up in a way
that's inappropriate we don't respect
the properties of the system we don't
end up with being able to realize those
analytical promises
indeed in practice the hamiltonian
usually decomposes into a potential
energy associated to position an
independent of momentum
and a kinetic energy associated to
momentum and invariant under position
changes both generating tractable flows
thanks to this decomposition
we are able to construct numerical
methods through splitting the vector
field
a few ideas coming together here
recalling some of our generalized
coordinate based approaches to
non-equilibrium steady States in
Bayesian mechanics and also
decomposition of complex functions
note also that for simplectic brackets
the existence of a shadow hamiltonian
can be guaranteed beyond the case of
splitting methods EG for variational
integrators which use a discrete version
of hamiltonians Hamilton's principle of
least action
and for most simplexic integrators in
which the simplexic bracket is preserved
up to topological considerations
described by the first Dirham Co
homology of face space so for discussion
with authors annual
what are the splitting integrators what
is split from what and why
what is the bracket notation or
operation and what is a poisson bracket
what is a poisson system
section 2 3 rate matching integrators
for smooth optimization
so having obtained a vast family of
smooth Dynamics and integrators that
closely preserve F we can now apply
these ideas to optimization
what is being set up in this section and
why
in equation seven we see that the
damping
coefficient gamma of T being greater
than zero reflects the dissipative
component or the second term in that
right hand side of equation seven so
damping coefficient controls the
strength of the dissipation one can
imagine that if the damping coefficient
is zero the dissipative side zeros out
and B has conservative Behavior
and so on so what is being set up here
and why
dot dot dot dot
the existence of such a lyopinent
function described above implies that
trajectory starting in the neighborhood
of Q star will converge to Q star
so it's like a ball rolling to the
bottom of a hill just like we've always
wanted
in other words the above system provably
solved the optimization problem minimum
of v on Q such that Q is in the D
dimensional real
punchline
we're setting up a system with good
smooth
optimization characteristics ball
rolling to the bottom of a smooth Hill
that is also on the path or using the
notation of or prepared to make the
transformation to
attractable discretization approach
so some more on the damping coefficient
they bring up some common choices for
the the damping coefficient
and Big O notation describes on the
order of which something occurs for
example linearly
order of the variable or sub or super
linearly as a function of time or data
points so in computational complexity
analysis people are often interested as
I double the amount of data I'm
analyzing does that make the algorithm
take twice as long that's linear
computational complexity does it take
four times as long does it take the same
amount of time and so on
and it'll be great to talk about
the intuitions and implications and
generalizations about how the damping
coefficient influences the computational
complexity estimates for convergence
in different settings
they write the conservative system from
equation 16 reduces precisely the
original dissipative system 13. the
second equation in 16 reproduces 14 and
the remaining equations are equivalent
to the equations of motion Associated to
13.
which in turn are equivalent to 8 as
previously noted
formally
what we have done is to embed the
original dissipative system with phase
space r 2D so real with 2D dimensions
into a higher dimensional conservative
system with base space r 2D plus two
the distributive Dynamics thus lies on a
hypersurface of constant energy k equals
zero in high dimensions
the reason for doing this procedure
called simplexification
is purely theoretical
oh come on it's not purely theoretical
since the theory of symplectic
integrators only accounts for
conservative systems we can now extend
this Theory to dissipative systems
settings by applying a simplectic
integrator to 13 and then fixing the
relevant coordinates 17 in the resulting
methods
geometrically this corresponds to
integrating the time flow exactly
we're going to talk about a relationship
between time and dissipative systems
after all its dissipative systems that
are dissipating in time and so
discretization of time plays a role in
the appropriate discretization
of a dissipative hamiltonian
and in citation 9 previously raised such
a procedure was defined under the name
of pre-symplectic integrators and these
connections hold not only for the
specific example above but also for
General non-conservative hamiltonian
systems so
what is happening here
what's an intuition for conservative and
dissipative systems and how have the
recent works of Franca at all expanded
what is possible
we are now ready to explain why this
approach is suitable to construct
practical optimization methods
the coordinate T sub K becomes simply
the time discretization which is exact
and so is U sub K since it is a function
of time alone
importantly U does not couple to any of
the other degrees of freedom so it is
irrelevant whether we have access to you
or not
because we're looking to solve a
function of t
17A
can be substituted in 15 to get 18 and
you can replace 13 to get 19.
we'll talk more about it with the
authors
therefore the known rates equation 11
for the Continuum system are nearly
preserved and so would be any rates of
more General time dependent dissipative
hamiltonian systems
let us now present an explicit algorithm
to solve the optimization problem
this is all happening as a consequence
of having a shadow hamiltonian
such that geometric integrators are able
to reproduce all the relevant properties
of the Continuum system
section 2.4 manifold and constrained
optimization following 10 we briefly
mentioned how the previous approach can
be extended in great generality to an
optimization problem so equation 21 we
present our minimization problem V of Q
variational Distribution on Q Citation
10 Franca at all
they write there are essentially two
ways to solve this problem through a
dissipative hamiltonian approach
one is to simulate a hamiltonian
Dynamics on T star M by incorporating
the metric of M in the kinetic moving
part of the hamiltonian
another is to consider a hamiltonian
Dynamics on r n and embed M into RN by
imposing several constraints
the first approach uses a li group we'll
talk more about it
an example of a second approach
one can constrain the integrator on RN
to define a simplecting integrator on M
via the discrete constrained variational
approach
by using some techniques
the above method consists in a
dissipative generalization of the
well-known rattle integrator from
molecular Dynamics citations 100 through
103.
used in computational biology
section 2.5 gradient flow has a high
friction limit
let us provide some intuition while
simulating second order systems is
expected to yield faster algorithms
as an illustration consider figure one
on the left we'll look at in a second
where a particle immersed in a fluid
falls under the influence of a potential
Force negative Delta sub Q on V and Q
so
partial differential with respect to Q
of v on Q
that plays a role of gravity and is
constrained a move on a Surface so ball
rolling down the hill we weren't joking
about it
in the underdamped case the particles
underwater which is not so viscous so it
has acceleration and moves fast it may
even oscillate in the overdamped case
the particle is in a highly viscous
fluid such as honey and the drag force
that
damping coefficient
gamma is comparable or stronger to the
gradient thus the particle moves slowly
since it cannot accelerate
during the same elapsed time delta T
an accelerated particle would travel a
longer distance
here's figure one
so here
why simulating second order systems
yields accelerated methods so on the
left constrained particle falling in
fluids of differential viscosity
here on the left we have the particle
falling through honey
it's slowly making its way to the bottom
of the bowl but it never really
builds speed its terminal velocity is
being dominated by the viscosity of the
fluid
whereas this ball falling through water
or falling through error is
with respect to the honey dampened Bowl
this is like an accelerated optimization
and they present some numerical results
that help us bolster that intuition
really
fun and embodied way to think about
optimization we've talked about that
ball rolling to the bottom of the hill
and what the ball does when it hits a
small bump but we have not talked about
what media
the balls floating through and the media
is the message and the fish doesn't know
what it's swimming through
section 2.6 optimization in the space of
probability measures it'll be great to
explore more because we're going to see
free energy calculations on the
stationary density KL Divergence and
more
for now we can just say all those
optimization techniques we were bringing
up earlier we're going to be able to do
them on information geometric spaces
that correspond to probability measures
that are well behaved not all
distributions are probability measures
or probability distributions just
because you draw a line doesn't mean you
can use that in part of your variational
inference scheme for Bayesian statistics
that's section two
on to section three
hamiltonian-based accelerated sampling
so we talked about the hamiltonian
conservative and dissipative and the
shadow hamiltonian which is going to be
orders of magnitude better to
approximate
we talked about gradient-based methods
and how accelerated sampling is going to
help us accelerate those sampling
techniques and now Section 3 brings it
together with hamiltonian based
accelerated sampling
section three
the purpose of sampling methods is to
efficiently draw samples from a target
distribution row or more commonly to
calculate expectations with respect to
row and from the end of the paragraph
an efficient sampling scheme is one that
minimizes the variance of the Monte
Carlo Markov chain estimator Monte Carlo
that means that we're sampling hands
from the poker table
and Markov chain which means that the
past only influences the future through
the present it's a quote memoryless
process
in other words fewer samples will be
needed to obtain a good estimate
intuitively good Samplers are Markov
chains that converge as fast as possible
to the Target distribution
it's like if you laid down a jump rope
on a mountain
if that jump rope converged quickly to
the Topography of the mountain it would
have been a fast converging jump rope
and we're doing something like that but
with sampling from the jump rope
3.1 optimizing diffusion processes for
sampling
as many mcmc methods are based on
discretizing continuous time stochastic
processes
the analysis of continuous time
processes is informative of the
properties of efficient samplers
and diffusion processes possess possess
a rich geometric Theory
extending that of vector fields and have
been widely studied in the context of
sampling
a lot of very fascinating ideas here
stratanovic stochastic differential
equations are going to come into play
equation 34.
more technical details on diffusion
the calculus of Twisted differential
forms
allows us to have a measure informed
calculus on multi-vector fields
what are twisted differential forms
I'm looking forward to that conversation
what is the untwisted differential form
have we been Twisted all along or not
and they go on to write a fundamental
Criterion for efficient sampling is
non-reversibility
a process is non-reversible if it is
statistically distinguishable from its
time reversal when initialized at the
target distribution so once the jump
rope is lying flat on the mountain it's
like in a position of reversibility
mixing metaphors
at will here
measure preserving diffusions are
non-reversible precisely when some
conditions are met
intuitively non-reversible processes
backtrack less often and thus furnish
more diverse samples so if you're that
ball rolling on the mountain you want to
just
plow forward and whether you're going up
or downhill you want to be sampling and
making moves
but you don't want to be going back and
forth because at that point it's not an
efficient sampling path
it's well known that removing
non-reversibility worsens the spectral
Gap and the asymptotic variants of the
mcmc estimator so time discretization
spectral Gap
in diffusions with linear coefficients
one can construct the optimal
non-reversible Matrix a to optimize the
spectral Gap
we can have well-behaved parameters that
help us get at optimal discretization
schemes so that that shadow hamiltonian
can be preserved when we do discretize
it during optimization so that we can
respect the Key properties of the system
however there are no generic guidelines
on how to optimize non-reversibility in
arbitrary diffusions this suggests a
two-step strategy to construct efficient
Samplers one optimize reversible
distributions diffusions and two add a
non-reversible perturbation
equation 36 citation 125.
diffusions are manifolds diffusion on
manifolds are reversible when certain
things are the case and they're not when
other things are the case
equation 37 we got a triangle pointing
down and a triangle pointing up
we're going to talk more about it
under damp language Dynamics
combine all the desirable properties of
an efficient sampler it is reversible
has degenerate noise and achieves
accelerated conversions to the Target
density
so
all of this groundwork
is helping us get to an analytical
formalization that's going to have the
right kind of properties so we can do
that discretization right on the shadow
hamiltonian so we can get the
accelerated optimization done
3.2 hamiltonian Monte Carlo
a challenging task consists of
constructing efficient sampling
algorithms with strong theoretical
guarantees
we now discuss an important family of
well-studied methods known as
hamiltonian Monte Carlo HMC which can be
implemented on any manifold for any
smooth fully supported Target measure
that is known up to a normalizing
constant
some of these methods can be seen as an
appropriate geometric integration of the
underdamped langevin diffusion
fusing down that Hill but in simpler it
is in general simpler to view them as
combining a geometrically integrated
deterministic Dynamics
with a simple stochastic process that
ensures erecticity
equation 38.
if we interpret the negative log density
V of Q
as a potential energy
eg a function depending on position Q
one can then plug in the potential
within Newton's equation
to obtain a deterministic proposal that
is well defined on any manifold as soon
as the acceleration and derivative
operators have been replaced by their
curved analogs so
what pulls the ball down the hill or if
you're an instrumentalist what force
describes the movement of the ball
moving down the hill
gravity
I think there's a John Mayer song about
it
surprises like gravity
it can be understood as the minimizing
force that pulls the ball down the hill
or describes the movement of the ball on
its path of least action down the hill
how cool
more discussion around 38.
bringing these ingredients together
we thus have the following HMC algorithm
given dot dot dot
we're going to compute a function
according to one a heat bath
two Shadow hamiltonian Dynamics and
three Metropolis correction
that's the recipe
we're bringing those ingredients
together
the above rudimentary HMC method was
proposed for simulations in lattice
Quantum chromodynamics with M being the
special unitary group s-u-n
and used a hamiltonian Dynamics
ingeniously constructed from the Maurer
carton frame to compute the partition
function of discretized gauge theories
this method has later been applied in
molecular Dynamics and statistics
there are three critical properties
underpinning the success
of HMC in practice
the first two are the preservation of
the reference measure and the existence
of a conserved Shadow hamiltonian for
the numerical method
the third critical property is the
existence of splitting's methods
for which all the composing flows are
either tractable or have adequate
approximations namely the geodesic
integrators
so geodesic geodesic methods
Buckminster Fuller tensegrity
synergetics
or however you think about geodesics as
paths in curved space
that is the kind of approximation and
splitting we're gaining access to with
appropriate discretizations on those
balls rolling to the bottom of the hill
let us also briefly mention some useful
upgrades that have been proposed in
recent years so for those who it's been
a few years since you checked in with
this domain this is a great place to
look first
you can grant the method extra
integration steps when the proposal is
rejected
or
you can use Criterion that aim to ensure
the motion is long enough to avoid
random walks but short enough that we do
not waste computational effort such as
the no u-turn sampler which is
integrated in a lot of software packages
second
modern HMC methods bypass this issue of
slow convergence
by replacing the heat bath with an
Ornstein old back process which ensures
the overall algorithm is irreversible an
OU process is like a Brownian diffusion
with a linear regression so it vibrates
and has volatility and it has a trend
line that's linear
third many modifications of the
rudimentary HMC algorithm only provide
improvements when the acceptance rate is
sufficiently high a third class of
upgrades improve the acceptance rate by
using the fact that the shadow
hamiltonian is exactly preserved by the
integrator
big point of the whole paper
finally the Metropolis step can be
replaced with a multinomial correction
that uses the entire numerical
trajectory accepting a given point along
it according to the degree by which it
distorts the target measure some
path-based inference methods with some
caveats
all right on to section four statistical
inference with kernel based
discrepancies so section four the
problem of parameter inference consists
of estimating an element Theta star
within big Theta using a sequence of
random functions or estimators Theta hat
n
of Omega onto big Theta
equations
conveniently reproducing kernel Hilbert
spaces rkhs are precisely Hilbert spaces
over which the duroc distributions which
is
a statistical distribution type where
it's like a spike at one location and
zero elsewhere
act continuously so
whether we're talking about events or
spiking neurons this is a really good
property
and more generally the probability
distributions that act continuously by
integration on in rkhsh are exactly
those for which all elements of H are
integrable
so analytically we have that nice
property
denoting by
fancy P sub H the set of such
probability measures such that dot dot
we can Define the maximum mean
discrepancy or MMD as such
more definitions a practical expression
for the squared MMD so just like in
linear regression we're often interested
in the sum of squared errors here we're
interested in the sum of squared MMD
4.1 topological methods for mmds just
remember mmds maximum mean discrepancy
a key feature of rkhs is that they are
hilbertian subspaces more details about
embedding in Hilbert spaces and
subspaces
the geometric analysis
the geometric description of rkhs and
MMD allows us to swiftly apply
topological methods in their analysis
there are reasons
this reduces the matter to a topological
question
instead
of defining T star to be the set of
probability measures
it is commonly done to Define
statistical manifolds it's desirable to
embed fancy P within a more structured
space such as the space of finite radon
measures
which enables the method to learn the
target function independently of the
data generating distribution
what is a radon measure we're going to
find out however
it enables the method to learn the
target function independently of the
data generating distribution sounds
pretty important if we want that Tale of
Two densities
MMD can discriminate distributions that
makes it useful to do other things
let's find out more
section 4.2 smooth measures and ksds
so
more information on mmds and about
making them computationally tractable
and citations to Stein's method are
provided for 195 which is the 1972 Stein
paper and 196 which is a paper written
by some of the authors about Stein's
method meet statistics a review of some
recent developments from 2021. and I
thought it'd be fun to look at some
figures from this paper and look at the
abstract so I'll put the figures up
above
Stein's method Compares probability
distributions through the study of a
class of linear operators called Stein
operators while mainly studied in
probability and used to underpin
theoretical statistics Stein's method
has led to significant advances in
computational statistics
the topics that are discussed in that
review
include tools to Benchmark and compare
sampling methods such as approximate
Markov chain Monte Carlo
deterministic alternatives to sampling
methods control variate techniques
parameter estimations and goodness of
fit testing and from the paper they
write
the list of results given in this paper
are but a mere sample
hey
of the ongoing activity in this newly
established area of research at the
boundary between probability functional
analysis data science and computational
statistics for instance Stein's method
has been used for Designing sampling
based algorithms for non-convex
optimization
learning semi-parametric multi-index
models in high dimensions and then
Bayesian statistics Stein discrepancies
have been used as variational objectives
for posterior optimization which is what
we're all about free energy functionals
using variational inference
as objectives for posterior
approximation of inference and action
free energy principle and these images
have some nice intuitions too here we
see
depending on our step size we're getting
different sampling
when our step size is to the negative
fifth power we're over sampling one part
of the space
then as we make the step size larger
our samples are drawn from different
distributions so that's selecting the
step size Epsilon for a stochastic
gradient language dynamic
and also from the Anastasia paper here's
another fun way to see that
here we have that bowl that we're
rolling the ball to the bottom of and
the Stein points and the Stein thinning
which is helping us understand maybe how
starting the ball in different locations
or critical locations accelerates what
we're doing with optimization so cool to
talk about
4.2.1 the canonical Stein operator and
poincare duality
there are two fundamental theorems that
help us understand the integral
differential geometry of the manifold
daram's theorem and the point Curry
duality
the former Durham's theorem relates the
topology of the manifold to information
on the solutions of differential
equations defined over the manifold
the latter which contains the
fundamental theorem of calculus
describes the properties of the integral
pairing Alpha Beta of differential forms
which include the pairing of test
functions with smooth measures
let's learn more about it
4.2.2 Colonel Stein discrepancies and
score matchings
technical definitions
facilitating Stein variational gradient
descent
4.3
information
geometry of mmds and natural gradient
descents
these tools have proved to be useful in
a wide range of contexts
more information about the Divergence
and how Divergence can improve the speed
of convergence
by following the natural gradient
descent
okay
red text speculation beware so the
operator
which is a phone routing system like
ring ring Hello Operator
is constructed in section 4.2.2 Colonel
Stein discrepancies and score matching
you can't have a t-test without the T
distribution
the t-test statistic
is using a t distribution
so a class of fancy V
a set fancy V of vector Fields or more
generally tensor fields
whose image F under the operator ring
ring has mean zero under mu
that's going to give us this discrepancy
the SD and the Stein variational
gradient descent so
there's some class of V Vector fields
such that the mean of something about
them is zero
does this enable
the central limit theorem or just
statistics more broadly
like the parametric and non-parametric
methods that we know and love from SPM
does that mean zero enable us to use
gaussian methods generalized gaussian
methods generalized linear methods SPM
and
does it enable the proposed smooth
distribution
the one generating the shadow
hamiltonian that's getting inferred over
to be interpreted or used truly as a
statistical distribution
it's easy to forget that not all
distributions are formal probability
distributions for example the area under
the curve from zero to one of a
probability distribution is one
something has to happen but not all
functions have an area under the curve
of 1 between 0 and 1.
so invariational Bayesian inference the
kind which we do in active inference
in fact the kind that's done in machine
learning and statistics more broadly but
were interested when action is a
parameter that we're doing inference on
we're concerned with the extremely
well-behaved properties of a certain
subset of distributions
so why are we doing this why is it
important that
we didn't need the input data that we
could construct measures that are
independent of the input data because we
want to enable the Tail of Two densities
we want to make generative models
that can be used generatively
generative AI
in the forward or the generative
Direction
but we also want to be able to enable
the recognition distribution which is
from empirical data to do hidden State
inference
and so just like least squares
regression
in the linear linear modeling case
where the sum of squares above and below
the regression line should be as low as
possible L2 Norm sum of squares
minimization
always works never complains
we want that kind of ball rolling to the
bottom of the hill
with free energy
functionals variational and expected
free energy functionals as the optimized
or satisficed imperative
for optimal perception which is signal
processing signals intelligence and
control which is control theory or
action selection
more technical details and equations 39b
and 39c
so what does it mean that the resulting
Stein discrepancy can be thought of as
an MMD that depends only on row and is
known as a kernel Stein discrepancy what
is that
as we did previously we can remove the
supermum by rewriting the above as a
supermum over some unit ball of
continuous linear functional
is this like simulating or modeling a
sphere rolling on a landscape like we've
been talking about
is the ball of optimal radius for
rolling on that landscape or what is
being optimized and what is the unit
the scaling or the scale specificity
that this scale-friendly sphere is
scaled to
equation 42 and 42a while in the
euclidean space yields the diffusion
score matching citation 204
barp at all again
minimum Stein discrepancy estimators
from 2019
they write
the main strength of our methodology is
its flexibility which allows us to
design estimators with desirable
properties for specific models at Hand
by carefully selecting a Stein
discrepancy we illustrate this Advantage
for several challenging problems for
score matching such as non-smooth
heavy-tailed or light-tailed densities
so again just with a little bit of
speculation here
and I think my camera has frozen
it's all good
all just go without the camera
okay
um one can estimate infer or optimize
the zero point and hence the variance
structure of the distribution
this is going to enable generalized
well-behaved modeling again from all of
those nice perspectives that we raised
earlier like gaussian Central limit
theorem smoothness statistical distance
euclidean all of those well-behaved
properties that we're looking for this
is going to help us get there
we are only talking about a specific
subset or type of landscape here the one
that we're doing variational inference
on that's the map
this is not the structure of the
territory
these well-behaved attributes of models
for better worse and different through
sickness and health
is because they're Maps
it is always the case that our
statistically nice generative models are
of a different structure or form than
the generative process so this is
actually not a criticism of quantitative
modeling as a process in fact this is
the entire basis of quantitative
modeling so we've approached this map
territory distinction map territory
fallacy fallacy fallacy from many angles
and one will still hear things like well
the structure of the statistical model
is not the same as the territory or how
can you say that the organism has these
well-behaved properties just because the
model does
and this brings a really sharp light on
it which is we're doing this insane
amount of analytical groundwork so that
the map has the good properties not to
constrain what the territory is so map
territory all of the math we've been
talking about is map we want
well-behaved Maps so that we can
describe well-behaved and unruly
territories
but it isn't the case that the organism
minimizes variational free energy it's
the generative model that minimizes
variational free energy so
a little bit of a leading discussion
topic or question for you all feel free
to give a thought in the live chat or
write a comment or join our discussions
how is this line of basic and
fundamental math research
by bark at all creating new models that
have the operational or denotational
semantics that we want for computational
statistics which is to say applied
information Theory
for example distributions that can be
interpreted or used as statistical
distributions ideally directly
compatible with current computational
methods SPM and Matlab pi mdp and Python
and Forney lab in Julia and so on
section
4.3.1 minimum Stein discrepancy
estimators
more technical details more citation to
204.
the parameters can be adjusted to
achieve characteristicness consistency
bias robustness and obtain Central limit
theorems c204
2019 paper with barbadol and let's just
look at a really cool image from that
paper figure one and figure two
pretty cool SD estimators
looking nice
section 4.3.2 likelihood free inference
with generative models so for many
applications of interests
the densities of the model mu subdata
cannot be evaluated or differentiated
we thus need density free inference
methods super convenient for Bayesian
statistics
more technical details information
tensor
under appropriate choices of kernels and
models one can derive theoretical
guarantees such as concentration and
generalization bounds consistency
asymptotic normality and robustness
so a little bit of a summary
we have good analytical and
computational footing in certain kinds
of situations or under certain
constraints so certainly not all
constraints but definitely for some
that might enable the efficient
computation not just specification but
actual implementation
of large generative models such as
described in the paper of fristian at
all 2022 designing ecosystems of
intelligence from shared sorry designing
ecosystems of intelligence from first
principles and they use the term
ecosystems of shared intelligence in
that paper
and so it's relevant to learn about the
actuality and build intuition why slash
how do we know well here's the one
figure in that paper of friction at all
the one figure
in this absolutely positional paper that
they have released
believes as parameters of a probability
distribution
here's the sharpening of a belief
as a distance belief updating
as traversing a statistical manifold
which is to say a lower dimensional
projected space
and what's being shown as the parameter
space of a probability distribution so
whether we see this as gradient Ascent
to climb to the top of the hill
or we take the negative and we have
gradient descent to the bottom of the
hill this is the figure chosen by some
very well-informed authors to describe
Bayesian mechanics
and
long last we get to section five
adaptive agents through active inference
we close as the authors write with a
generic use case called active inference
a general framework for describing and
designing adaptive agents that unifies
all aspects of behavior including
perception planning and learning as
processes of inference
by exploiting this geometric structure
in a generic framework for Designing
adaptive agents we derive the objective
functional overarching decision making
and describe its information geometric
structure
revealing several special cases that are
established Notions in statistics
cognitive science and engineering
so section 5.1 modeling adaptive
decision making
first they're going to talk about
Behavior agents and environments
behavior is going to be defined as the
interaction between an agent and its
environment
and the system is going to describe the
agent plus its environments
there's going to be a set of states that
are partitions from a state space big X
external States s are going to be
unknown to the agent and constitute the
environment
States belonging to the agent pi
particular States
are going to be a subset of two
different things so here is s which is
here external States note that in some
other settings s will refer to sensory
States so look at the notation in this
paper
and Pi which in other papers is
sometimes used to describe policy
inference here is going to describe
particular States
so Pi is O and A O are the observable
States states that the agent can see but
cannot directly control sense States
and a are the autonomous States states
that the agencies and can directly
control and those are going to be
internal States and active States
bigger two has a great representation
and again note the way that Pi s o and a
are being used in this paper
s is the external process
hidden State latent State causal
inference
o are the observations
and
the agent process consists of Pi
which is the observations and alpha or a
a is consisting of according to the
particular partition two different kinds
of states which is
internal States cognitive States
and action States and so we're going to
compute bounds
for free energy functionals with a
special focus on autonomous processes
because controlling our perception
is not possible and maybe not even
preferable by controlling it at the
level of what we observe
but rather if we control our internal
states which is our interpretation of
the perception and our action States
will be doing optimal perception and
optimal action so those are the two
sides of the coin with
inference as perception slash learning
and action selection that's how a unify
action and inference in active inference
is by caring about the bounding of
self-suprisal just like gravity on our
autonomous processes so this will be
super fun to discuss more
5.1.2 decision making in precise agents
so what distinguishes people from small
particles
people are subject to classical as
opposed to statistical mechanics check
out active live stream 49 for more on
Bayesian mechanics and some of these
distinctions with classical statistical
Quantum and Thermo
in other words they are precise agents
with conservative Dynamics
precise agent definition 5.1 an Asian is
precise when it evolves
deterministically in a possibly
stochastic environment
more definitions
and it's useful here to highlight first
and then all's recent paper path
integrals particular kinds and strange
things which provides a taxonomy of
things taxonomy of
particular entities
that run the gamut of sophistication
from inert particles which have no
active States
active particles which have active
States
conservative particles which have
cognitive dynamics that are described as
classical and strange particles which
represent in this visualization the
highest level of cognitive
sophistication in which those internal
hidden States
themselves have this kind of what would
happen if this happens counterfactual
type or thinking through other Minds
type cognitive model structure
doing forward and inverse inference on
these
great times
5.1.2 decision making and precise agents
we have mathematical formalisms for
decisions preferences and predictions
all using the partitioned variables
5.1.2 more formalisms we get to
expected free energy expected free
energy is
equation 41k
active inference is
Hamilton's principle of least action on
expected free energy
and expresses the most likely decision
where
certain features are met
principle of least action on manifolds
of inference and action
subsuming or bringing together
inference and action active inference
free energy principle
5.1.3 active inference framework aif
looks like it describes agents that
engage in purposeful Behavior
we can rearrange the expected free
energy efe in several ways Each of which
reveals a fundamental trade-off that
underwrites decision making
this allows us to relate active
inference to information theoretic
formalizations of decision making that
predominate in statistics cognitive
science and engineering
figure three
as hinted at in the early early keywords
here on the top we have the general
formalizations of active inference and
one of the partitions or better to say
decompositions is shown here where
extrinsic value is the surprisal about
observations
making sure that what we're getting in
observations are what we expect slash
prefer if the body wants to be expecting
homeostatic temperature that's what this
is going to determine and it plays a
role equivalent to reward in reward and
reinforcement learning based approaches
because we don't need to actually set a
reward function but we get something
that looks like self-suprisal aligned
with reward using the preference
variable over observations
a lot more to say there
in the second term is the intrinsic
value the epistemic value
curiosity novelty learning reduction of
uncertainty
and another partitioning is between risk
and ambiguity
there are four colored dots
red tan gray and blue corresponding to
special cases so
under the setting where there's no
ambiguity
we realize or manifest the special case
where control can be seen as inference
maximum entropy reinforcement learning
prospect theory and KL optimal control
this is like doing as good as you can
strategically or tactically given that
there's no ambiguity in how your
decisions play out
now under the setting where there's no
ambiguity or preferences
a maximum entropy principle is realized
and work with Bayesian mechanics and
Dalton at all has shown that the
constrained maximum entropy principle is
dual to the fep
in the case of no extrinsic value so no
quote reward no quote goals we don't use
reward or goals in the octave inference
ontology
but borrowing those words from some long
long forgotten ontology
in the case of no extrinsic value
we re we realize the special case of
Maximum Information Gain Bayesian
experimental design so not to prove or
disprove but the maximally informative
experiment that's the Bayesian
scientific epistemology
intrinsic motivation and Bayesian
surprise
seeking out optimally informative
stimuli
and contrast that with a setting where
there's no intrinsic value
so where there's nothing to learn
we realize expected utility Theory
Bayesian decision Theory reinforcement
learning and optimal control
so special cases
from many different fields ranging from
statistical mechanics to Bayesian
decision making and statistics
integrated or perhaps better generalized
across
in the formalisms of active inference
which
is something like
a Hamilton's principle of least action
on variational or expected free energy
expressing the most likely inference and
action under certain constraints not the
most rewarding but the most likely
5.1.3 decision making minimizes both
risk and ambiguity risk
first term on the right hand side
ambiguity second term
minimizing ambiguity leads to a type of
observational bias commonly known as the
streetlight effect when a person loses
their keys at night they initially
search for them under the street light
because of the resulting observations
I see my keys under the street light
or I do not see my keys under the street
light accurately disambiguate external
states of Affairs
first place to look makes sense under
the street light and the last place you
look is where you find it
more in 5.1.3 decision making maximizes
extrinsic and intrinsic value another
decomposition of the formalisms of
active inference maximizing information
gained leads to a goal directed form of
exploration driven to answer what would
happen if I did that
true counterfactuals
this decision-making procedure
underwrites Bayesian experimental design
in statistics which describes optimal
experiments as those that maximize
expected Information Gain and we've had
some great discussions recently in
textbook groups and in discussion hours
where we contrasted that
falsificationist concept of accept or
reject a hypothesis
and even the idea of a scientist or a
researcher setting out to accept or
reject hypothesis whether you take that
positivist
or
you take the other path of
falsificationism
in both cases you might end up with an
informative experiment or not but you
can easily imagine cases where you end
up with an uninformative experiment
because you set out to confirm something
you knew or you set out to disprove
something by constraining your
experiment so that it was locally
disproven
in contrast when we take into account
the richness of our generative model
we motivate this Bayesian epistemology
and ultimately professional bayesianism
where we make optimal experiments in
terms of their maximum expected
Information Gain which requires you to
also State your generative model
decision making under active inference
weighs the imperatives of maximizing
utility and Information Gain which
suggests a principled solution to the
exploration exploitation dilemma
great point to jump into does active
inference simply by written down by
being written down on a paper resolve or
transcend or dissolve exploration
exploitation
no
does it provide a space or a framework a
method an approach software packages
research community that can help us
address and navigate and surf on the
edge of that dilemma absolutely
5.2.1 the basic active inference
algorithm we're going to go through it
with authors
preferential inference we want to infer
preferences about external and
observable trajectories
two
for each possible sequence of past
present and future actions a
we're going to engage in both sides of
the coin perceptual inference
what would I perceive if that happened
and planning as inference assess the
action sequence by evaluating its
expected free energy
and then
three decision making execute the most
likely decision at t plus one According
to some distributions
sample from your action posterior
action prior that's like your habits it
gets sharpened or modified with expected
free energy and then you sample from the
action posterior
5.2.1 sequential decision making under
uncertainty
a partially observable Markov decision
process pomdp is a discrete time model
of how actions influence external States
in a pomdp
each external State depends only on the
current action and previous external
State that's the Markov property
each observation depends only on the
current external state
and one can additionally specify a
distribution of preferences over
external trajectories
one and two form the agent's po mdp
prediction model
two and three form the agent's hidden
Markov preference model which defines
the active inference agent
a simple simulation of active inference
on a pomdp is provided in figure four
implementation details on generic pomdps
are available for more complex
simulations of sequential decision
making
EG involving hierarchical plmdps please
see
citations
figure four
it's a prediction model
this is sequential decision making in a
t maze environment
on the left the agent's prediction model
as a PO mdp represented here as a
Bayesian Network
on the right information on the
teammates so
here
we have some type of Bayesian graph
reflecting
hopefully
a statistical system that's going to
have all of these well-behaved
properties that we've been talking about
in the paper
and
then
the teammate is played out
we'll talk about it
5.2.3 World model learning is inference
due to a lack of domain knowledge it may
be challenging to specify an agent's
prediction and preference model for
example how do external States map to
observations should external States be
represented in a discrete or continuous
State space
also some great questions that come up
every day and are addressed in chapter
six a recipe for active inference
modeling by the par pazulo and friston
2022 textbook
so how do we get the right priors or at
least approximately adequate priors
one way to answer the question lies in
optimizing a free energy functional f
which is an Evidence lower bound
we see here variational free energy
decomposed into an energy minus entropy
and decomposed into a complexity minus
accuracy
framing
maximizing accuracy usually results in
generative models involving Universal
function approximators
minimizing complexity results in
organizing representations in sparse
compartmentalized and hierarchical
generative models
where higher levels of a hierarchy
encode more abstract representations and
vice versa
a computationally efficient method to
compare priors by their free energy is
Bayesian model reduction
free energy unifies inference and model
selection under a single objective
function
5.2.4 scaling active inference
planning for all possible courses of
action is computationally expensive
one way to finesse this is by planning
only for intelligently chosen subsets of
action sequences using sampling
algorithms like Monte Carlo tree search
if you're interested in that check out
the recent research on branching time
active inference
similarly Monte Carlo sampling finesses
the expectations inherent in assessing
action sequences
a complementary approach is to assess
actions instead of action sequences
by conditioning all future actions to be
optimal in the sense that they minimize
the expected free energy
it leads to smarter agents whose
computational complexity scales linearly
as opposed to exponentially in the
length of action sequence
let's learn more about it
scalable inference methods can be used
to make active inference more efficient
we can train neural networks to predict
the various posterior distributions
including the posterior over actions
while training the output of the neural
network can be used as an initial
conditions for variational inference
resulting inaccurate inferences whose
computational costs decrease as the
network learns
additionally optimizing free energy
reduces to efficient message passing
schemes when one imposes certain
simplifying restrictions to the family
of candidate distributions lots of
really exciting work in neurobiology and
statistics around message passing
getting close to the end here
a much cheaper implementation of active
inference exists for continuous States
evolving in continuous time
pretty cool par at all 2022 textbook
chapter 7 discrete time active inference
standard models chapter 8 continuous
time
active inference models
this method frames perception and
decision making as variational inference
by simulating a gradient flow on free
energy in an extended state space
it can be combined with discrete active
inference to operate efficiently in
generative models combining discrete and
continuous States
we talked about that in live stream 46
active inference does not contradict
folk psychology discrete active
inference decision-making active
inference Dai and continuous time motor
active inference
being used together
also seen in the paradol textbook as an
example High dimensional observations in
the continuous domain EG speech
processed through continuous active
inference are converted into discrete
abstract representations EG semantics
and we can even go further and say
rhetorical and narrative information
spaces
based on these representations the agent
makes high-level categorical decisions
EG I want to move over there
which contextualize low-level continuous
actions EG The Continuous motion of a
limb towards the goal location
and that is how the paper ends so
closing thoughts if anybody wants to
write a comment live feel free to do so
we'll be over very shortly
what are the implications of this work
we have an open
space to talk about it
what questions and discussion topics are
you interested in
please write comments before or after
the dot one and the dot two so we can
have those interesting discussions
and just as a little bit of a closer
I'll share some stable diffusion
images that were generated using the
paper title
as well as various other terms free
energy
lots of fun images
a lot of good balance to some of the
technical aspects that were being
described in the paper was good to look
at what diffusion looks like
aesthetically
and so
that is the end of this live stream 52.0
I hope that you found it useful that
you're interested to act infer serve to
learn more contribute more write a
comment
make it happen in your own life or in
your own way with this
honestly challenging paper
so if you've listened this far
thanks a lot for your attention and
looking forward to 51 I'm sorry
52.1 and 0.2 when
we will speak with some authors and some
of you so
till next time
thanks again and see you in the dot one
foreign